William G. Niederland Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
William G. Niederland Papers 1810-1982 (bulk 1952-1982)
MSS60467
Niederland, William G., 1904-
5,950 items
17 containers
6.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Psychoanalyst, educator, and author. Correspondence, writings, lectures, patient files, and other papers pertaining primarily to Niederland's career in the field of psychoanalysis.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Arlow, Jacob A.--Correspondence.; Kinzelmann, Dietlind--Art.; Köhler, Lotte, 1925-2022--Correspondence.; Lewin, Bertram D. (Bertram David), 1896-1971--Correspondence.; Lingens, Ella--Correspondence.; Loch, Wolfgang--Correspondence.; Niederland, William G., 1904-1993.; Niederland, William G., 1904-1993. Schreber case: psychoanalytic profile of a paranoid personality. 1974.; Quen, Jacques M., 1928- --Correspondence.; Schliemann, Heinrich, 1822-1890.; Schreber, Daniel Paul, 1842-1911.
Organizations
Downstate Medical Center (N.Y.); New York Psychoanalytic Institute. Kris Study Group. New York Psychoanalytic Institute. Kris Study Group records.
Subjects
Abnormalities, Human--Psychological aspects.; Creative ability.; Geography--Psychological aspects.; Holocaust survivors--Psychology.; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945)--Psychological aspects.; Paranoia.; Psychoanalysis--Practice--New Jersey.; Psychoanalysis--Practice--New York (State); Psychoanalysis--Societies, etc.; Psychoanalysis--Study and teaching--New York (State)--New York.; Psychoanalysis.
Occupations
Authors.; Educators.; Psychoanalysts.
Provenance
The papers of William G. Niederland, psychoanalyst, educator, and author, were given by Niederland to the Library of Congress in 1982 and 1983. A small addition was given by the Sigmund Freud Archives in 1987.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of William G. Niederland are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1904, Aug. 19 Born, Schippenbeil, Germany
1929 M.D., University of Würzburg, Würzburg, Germany
1929 1930 Residency, Beelitz Heilstätten, Berlin, Germany
1930 1932 Public health official, Düsseldorf, Germany
1932 1934 Medical director, Rheinburg Sanatorium for Nervous and Mental Diseases, Gailingen, Germany
1934 1938 Private practice in Milan, Italy, after fleeing Nazi Germany
1940 Immigration to United States
1941 1946 Private practice in New York, N.Y., and clinical assistant, Mount Sinai Hospital, New York, N.Y.
1947 1953 Psychoanalytic training, New York Psychoanalytic Institute, New York, N.Y.
1949 Published Man-Made Plague: A Primer on Neurosis. New York: Renbayle House
1952 Married Jacqueline Rosenberg
1952 1974 Private practice in New York, N.Y.
1952 1977 Taught, Downstate Medical Center, Brooklyn, N.Y.; professor emeritus after 1977
1958 1974 Chief consulting psychiatrist, Altro Health and Rehabilitation Services, New York, N.Y.
1958 1980 Coeditor, Psychoanalytic Quarterly
1971 Published Psychic Traumatization: Aftereffects in Individuals and Communities. Boston: Little, Brown, and Co.
1971 1973 President, Psychoanalytic Association of New York
1974 Published The Schreber Case: Psychoanalytic Profile of a Paranoid Personality. New York: Quadrangle/New York Times Book Co. Private practice in Englewood, N.J.
1993, July 30 Died, Englewood, N.J.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of William G. Niederland (1904-1993) span the years 1810-1982, with the bulk of the material dating from 1952 to 1982. The collection documents Niederland's work in the field of psychoanalysis as an author, educator, and clinician. The papers consist of correspondence, patient files, drafts of writings and lectures, research files, and material from professional organizations. They are organized in five series: Correspondence, Patient File, Subject File, Writings File, and Miscellany.
Niederland, a native of Germany, practiced medicine in Europe for ten years before immigrating to the United States in 1940. He was born in 1904 in Schippenbeil, East Prussia, the son of an orthodox rabbi. After receiving a medical degree from the University of Würzburg in 1929, Niederland worked for several years in Berlin, Düsseldorf, and Gailingen. In 1934, he fled Nazi Germany and established a private psychiatric practice in Milan. With the signing of the Italian-German military alliance in 1939, Niederland once again fled fascism. After a brief stay in a refugee camp in England, he secured a position as a doctor and surgeon on a British merchant ship. In December 1940, American officials permitted him to enter the United States.
Between 1947 and 1953, Niederland underwent formal psychoanalytic training at the New York Psychoanalytic Institute. For over thirty years, he maintained private practices in New York and New Jersey and held professional positions at Mount Sinai Hospital, Altro Health and Rehabilitation Services, and Haversack General Hospital. He taught for twenty years at the Downstate Medical Center in Brooklyn, New York. Niederland served as coeditor of Psychoanalytic Quarterly from 1958 to 1980 and president of the Psychoanalytic Association of New York from 1971 to 1973.
Niederland researched and wrote on numerous topics. In 1951, he published his first work on Daniel Paul Schreber, a case made famous by Sigmund Freud's analysis of Schreber's memoirs in 1911. Niederland's analysis focused particularly on Schreber's childhood and his relationship with his father, Dr. Daniel Gottlieb Moritz Schreber. Niederland wrote numerous papers on the subject and in 1974 published The Schreber Case: Psychoanalytic Profile of a Paranoid Personality. Beginning in the early 1960s, Niederland developed the concept of the "survivor syndrome" in working with survivors of the Nazi Holocaust. He found that survivors experience unresolved feelings of guilt and grief that lead to depression, anxiety, insomnia, personality change, and hyperamnesia.
Niederland also applied psychoanalytic research methods to the study of creativity and the creative process. He noted the frequency of perplexing and often tragic experiences, such as illness or physical disabilities, encountered by creative people during childhood. He found that such experiences enhanced their emotional reactivity and responsiveness to internal and external stimuli. Niederland also coined the term "psychogeography," a field of study that examines underlying psychological forces operative in geographical pursuits such as exploration and analyzes the anthropomorphic nature of explorers' views of the earth.
The Correspondence series consists largely of letters sent and received from colleagues in the United States and Europe. The correspondence is primarily personal and largely concerns Niederland's research and writings. Prominent correspondents include Jacob A. Arlow, Lotte Köhler, Bertram D. Lewin, Ella Lingens, Wolfgang Loch, and Jacques M. Quen.
The Patient File includes notes from therapy sessions conducted largely in the 1960s. The case of Arline Blackman is particularly well documented and was used by Niederland to study the psychological effect of facial disfigurement.
The largest group of papers in the Subject File concerns the Kris study group established by Ernst Kris at the New York Psychoanalytic Institute. These files consist of minutes, case presentations, and memoranda dating just prior to Kris' death in February 1957 and continuing into the 1970s. Niederland's work in Europe is documented through correspondence while he was in Milan and a series of reference letters written for him between 1930 and 1940. The series also contains research material on such topics as creativity and psychogeography. The Subject File also includes Niederland's research on Heinrich Schliemann, the "father" of modern archeology. Included are photocopies of original Schliemann correspondence given to Niederland by a member of Schliemann's family.
The Writing File contains drafts, notes, and correspondence related to Niederland's writings. The largest group of material concerns Niederland's research on the Schreber case, focusing in particular on Schreber's family and childhood. The series also includes published and unpublished writings by others collected by Niederland or sent to him by colleagues.
The Miscellany series includes information about Niederland's education, awards, and appointments. The series also includes examples of the artwork of Dietlind Kinzelmann who sent her work to Niederland after reading his analysis of the creative process. Also included is printed matter largely from professional conferences and organizations.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in five series:
Correspondence, 1946-1982
Patient File, circa 1953-1971
Subject File, 1868-1981
Writing File, 1810-1982
Miscellany, 1922-1981
Container List
- Correspondence, 1946-1982 (Box 1-3)
  Correspondence and attached and related material.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - "A-D" miscellaneous, 1952-1981, undated, (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Ehebald, Ulrich, 1964-1978 (Box 1)
  - "E" miscellaneous, 1964-1980, undated (Box 1)
  - "F-G" miscellaneous, 1952-1981, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Herberg, Hans-Joachim, 1976-1981 (Box 1)
  - "H" miscellaneous, 1969-1981 (Box 1)
  - "I-K" miscellaneous, 1952-1982, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Lewin, Bertram D., 1950-1970, undated (Box 1)
  - Lingens, Ella, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - Loch, Wolfgang, 1975-1977, undated (Box 1)
  - "L" miscellaneous, 1952-1981 (Box 2)
  - "M" miscellaneous, 1962-1981 (Box 2)
  - Niederland family, 1974-1980, undated (Box 2)
  - "N" miscellaneous, 1967-1980 (Box 2)
  - "O-P" miscellaneous, 1961-1980, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Quen, Jacques M., 1975 (Box 2)
  - "R-T" miscellaneous, 1946-1981, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Venzlaff, Ulrich, 1977-1982 (Box 2)
  - "V" miscellaneous, 1958-1981 (Box 2)
  - "W-Z" miscellaneous, 1953-1981, (3 folders) (Box 3)
- Patient File, circa 1953-1971 (Box 3-4)
  Notes and correspondence concerning individuals treated by Niederland.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of patient.
  - "A" miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Baker, Jo Ann, 1961 (Box 3)
  - Blackman, Arline, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - "C-K" miscellaneous, (8 folders) (Box 3)
  - "L-Z" miscellaneous, (9 folders) (Box 4)
- Subject File, 1868-1981 (Box 4-7)
  Correspondence, minutes, research files, biographical material, academic calendars, notes, and printed matter chiefly concerning Niederland's professional associations and research in the United States.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material.
  - Biographical material, 1954-1981 (Box 4)
  - Italy, private practice in Milan, 1935-1939 (Box 4)
  - Kris, Ernst, study group, New York Psychoanalytic Institute, New York, N.Y. (Box 4)
    - 1957-1958, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1959-1962, (7 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1963-1978, (7 folders) (Box 6)
  - Miscellany, 1906, 1968-1973, undated (Box 6)
  - Mount Airy Foundation, Denver, Colo., gold medal award, 1979-1980 (Box 6)
  - Notes, 1961-1977, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Psychogeography, 1970-1978 (Box 7)
  - Reference letters written for Niederland, 1930-1940 (Box 7)
  - Requests for publications, 1969-1980 (Box 7)
  - Schliemann, Heinrich, research file (Box 7)
    - General correspondence, 1961-1976, (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - Photocopies of Schliemann correspondence, 1868-1870 (Box 7)
  - State University of New York, Downstate Medical Center, Brooklyn, N.Y., 1972-1978 (Box 7)
- Writing File, 1810-1982 (Box 7-15)
  Drafts, correspondence, research files, reviews, and printed matter organized into writings by Niederland and by others.
  Niederland's writings are arranged alphabetically by type of publication and alphabetically therein by title. Writings by others are arranged alphabetically by name of author, with jointly-written and unidentified works filed last.
  - By Niederland (Box 7)
    - Books (Box 7)
      - Miscellaneous, 1948-1980, undated (Box 7)
      - The Schreber Case (Box 7)
        - Drafts (Box 7)
          - Editorial note (Box 7)
          - Introduction (Box 7)
          - Miscellaneous pages (Box 7)
          - Table of contents (Box 7)
        - General correspondence, 1957-1978 (Box 8)
        - Lectures by Niederland, 1950-1974, undated (Box 8)
        - Miscellany, 1958-1978, undated (Box 8)
        - Research file (Box 8)
          - Biographical material, 1876, 1950 (Box 8)
          - Excerpts from "Denkswürdigkeiten" and medical testimony concerning Schreber, 1899-1901 (Box 8)
          - Genealogical data (Box 8)
            - Death certificates of maternal antecedents, 1810-1871 (Box 8)
            - General, 1958-1960, undated (Box 8)
          - Notes (Box 8)
          - Photographs (Box 8)
          - Schreber, Daniel Gottlieb Moritz, and early history of the "Schreber-Vereine," 1861-1960 (Box 8)
        - Reviews, 1976-1979, undated (Box 8)
        - Schatzmann, Dr. Morton, alleged plagiarism of Niederland's work, 1973 (Box 8)
    - Comments on papers, 1961-1980 (Box 8)
    - Discussion transcripts (Box 9)
      - Aggression study conference and group, 1970-1973 (Box 9)
      - "The Creative Process," 1979 (Box 9)
    - Lectures, 1945-1982, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Letters to newspaper editors, 1978-1981 (Box 9)
    - Miscellany, 1965-1981, undated (Box 9)
    - Papers (Box 9)
      - "Analytic Approaches to Artistic Creativity," 1975, undated (Box 9)
      - "An Analytic Inquiry into the Life and Work of Heinrich Schliemann" (1972), 1964-1980 For additional material see Container 7, Schliemann, Heinrich, research file (Box 10)
      - "An Analytic Inquiry into the Sources and History of the Name America," 1964-1971, undated, (2 folders) (Box 10)
      - "B-C" miscellaneous, 1956-1978, undated (Box 10)
      - "E-N" miscellaneous, 1959-1975, undated, (2 folders) (Box 10)
      - "On River Symbolism," 1956-1957, undated (Box 10)
      - "On the Writing of Biographies," undated (Box 11)
      - "P-R" miscellaneous, 1964-1978, undated, (2 folders) (Box 11)
      - Schreber, Daniel Paul, 1951-1963, undated, (3 folders) (Box 11)
      - "S-T" miscellaneous, 1938-1976, undated (Box 11)
  - By others (Box 11)
    - "A-Bl" miscellaneous (Box 11)
    - "Br-J" miscellaneous, (5 folders) (Box 12)
    - "K-L" miscellaneous (Box 13)
    - Masson, J. Moussaieff, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - "M" miscellaneous (Box 13)
    - "N-St" miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - "Sw-Z" miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 14)
    - Joint authors (Box 15)
    - Unidentified (Box 15)
- Miscellany, 1922-1981 (Box 15-17)
  Awards, certificates, artwork, photographs, and printed matter.
  - Awards, certificates, and appointments, 1922-1981, undated (Box 15)
  - Kinzelmann, Dietlind, artwork with comments by Niederland, 1978 (Box 15)
  - Photographs (Box 15)
  - Printed matter, (4 folders); (3 folders) (Box 16, Box 17)